<chapter id="Migration_from_older_versions">
    <title>Migration from older versions</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Migrating from 1.0 Alpha 4 to Beta 1</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                DB Schema has changed.  We have added export of the database to Beta 1, but not the ability to import
                the database from older versions. This will be supported in future releases.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                For all clients except bearer-only applications, you must specify at least one redirect uri.  Keycloak
                will not allow you to log in unless you have specified a valid redirect uri for that application.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                Resource Owner Password Credentials flow is now disabled by default. It can be enabled by setting the toggle
                for <literal>Direct Grant API</literal> <literal>ON</literal> under realm config in the admin console.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                Configuration is now done through <literal>standalone/configuration/keycloak-server.json</literal>. This
                should mainly affect those that use MongoDB.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                JavaScript adapter has been refactored. See the <link linkend='javascript-adapter'>JavaScript adapter</link> section for more details.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                The "Central Login Lifespan" setting no longer exists.  Please see the <link linkend='session-timeouts'>Session Timeout</link> section
                for me details.
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Migrating from 1.0 Alpha 2 to Alpha 3</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                SkeletonKeyToken, SkeletonKeyScope, SkeletonKeyPrincipal, and SkeletonKeySession have been renamed to:
                AccessToken, AccessScope, KeycloakPrincipal, and KeycloakAuthenticatedSession respectively.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                ServleOAuthClient.getBearerToken() method signature has changed.  It now returns an AccessTokenResponse
                so that you can obtain a refresh token too.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                Adapters now check the access token expiration with every request.  If the token is expired, they will
                attempt to invoke a refresh on the auth server using a saved refresh token.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                Subject in AccessToken has been changed to the User ID.
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Migrating from 1.0 Alpha 1 to Alpha 2</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                DB Schema has changed.  We don't have any data migration utilities yet as of Alpha 2.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                JBoss and Wildfly adapters are now installed via a JBoss/Wildfly subsystem.  Please review the adapter
                installation documentation.  Edits to standalone.xml are now required.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                There is a new credential type "secret".  Unlike other credential types, it is stored in plain text in
                the database and can be viewed in the admin console.

            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                There is no longer required Application or OAuth Client credentials.  These client types are now
                hard coded to use the "secret" credential type.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                Because of the "secret" credential change to Application and OAuth Client, you'll have to update
                your keycloak.json configuration files and regenarate a secret within the Application or OAuth Client
                credentials tab in the administration console.
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
</chapter>